<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Dave Rosborough</title>
    <link>http://faith.rosborough.ca/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Dave Rosborough</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2015 21:41:24 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://faith.rosborough.ca/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>One Thing You Never Tire Of</title>
      <link>http://faith.rosborough.ca/one_thing_you_never_tire_of/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2015 21:41:24 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://faith.rosborough.ca/one_thing_you_never_tire_of/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This morning, on my way to visit a friend, I was tuned into the local Christian radio station.  The hosts were encouraging people to call in and answer the following question:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Name one thing you never get tired of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I listened, they read out some of the answers that listeners had called in: Starbucks.  Disneyland.  One listener said &amp;ldquo;the laughter of children&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what do you never get tired of?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, in the few minutes I listened, no one mentioned a &lt;em&gt;person&lt;/em&gt;.  Not their kids (just their laughter), not their spouse, not their parents, not their significant other.  Perhaps because it&amp;rsquo;s easy to get tired of people - we&amp;rsquo;re not perfect.  I, for one, can be a bit annoying at times.  It&amp;rsquo;s probably pretty tough to &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; get tired of me once in a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d like to say I was surprised that no one mentioned anything to do with God - but really, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t expecting much.  Church didn&amp;rsquo;t come up.  Maybe that&amp;rsquo;s because church is filled with &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt;.  Jesus wasn&amp;rsquo;t mentioned - maybe that would have been too spiritual.  The book of Leviticus wasn&amp;rsquo;t high on the list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;King David may have actually been surprised by that last omission.  Psalm 119, after all, is essentially a love song to the Law of God.  Listen to some of the language David uses to describe the Law:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the way of your testimonies I delight as much as in all riches.  - Psalm 119:14&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will delight in your statutes; I will not forget your word.  - Psalm 119:16&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My soul is consumed with longing for your rules at all times.  - Psalm 119:20&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your testimonies are my delight; they are my counselors.  - Psalm 119:24&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cling to your testimonies, O LORD; let me not be put to shame!  - Psalm 119:31&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lead me in the path of your commandments, for I delight in it.  - Psalm 119:35&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Behold, I long for your precepts; in your righteousness give me life!  - Psalm 119:40&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For I find my delight in your commandments, which I love.  I will lift up my hands toward your commandments, which I love, and I will meditate on your statutes.  - Psalm 119:47-48&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let your mercy come to me, that I may live; for your law is my delight.  - Psalm 119:77&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your law had not been my delight, I would have perished in my affliction.  - Psalm 119:92&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh how I love your law! It is my meditation all the day.  - Psalm 119:97&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your testimonies are my heritage forever, for they are the joy of my heart.  - Psalm 119:111&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore I love your commandments above gold, above fine gold.  - Psalm 119:127&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I open my mouth and pant, because I long for your commandments.  - Psalm 119:131&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He keeps going - but I think you get the idea.  Here is a man using the sort of language I &lt;em&gt;wish&lt;/em&gt; I could think of to write in an anniversary card for my wife - and he&amp;rsquo;s using it about Leviticus and Deuteronomy.  He &lt;em&gt;delights&lt;/em&gt;, he &lt;em&gt;is consumed&lt;/em&gt;, he &lt;em&gt;clings&lt;/em&gt;, he &lt;em&gt;longs for&lt;/em&gt;, he &lt;em&gt;loves&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why?  How?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a teenager, I was stymied several times in my attempt to read through the Bible - mostly by these very passages that David is writing love songs about.  I didn&amp;rsquo;t love them - they were &lt;em&gt;boring&lt;/em&gt;.  Perhaps you might agree with me.  Maybe we harbour a suspicion that David is applying a bit of poetic license - maybe we think he&amp;rsquo;s exaggerating just a little.  I mean, really - &amp;ldquo;I open my mouth and pant, because I long for your commandments&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the content of the rest of David&amp;rsquo;s written output, and the things written elsewhere about his life, it&amp;rsquo;s a pretty tough argument to claim that he&amp;rsquo;s just faking it.  We have no real reason to believe that he&amp;rsquo;s lying, other than a sense of incredulousness arising from our own shortcomings.  But what motivates David&amp;rsquo;s passion for the Word?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look back through those verses I quoted above, and I think you&amp;rsquo;ll see what it is.  Specifically, look for the word right &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; &amp;ldquo;law&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;testimonies&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;statutes&amp;rdquo;.  Each and every time, in these verses, it points to a &lt;em&gt;person&lt;/em&gt;.  It&amp;rsquo;s not &amp;ldquo;the law&amp;rdquo;, it&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;your law&amp;rdquo;.  Not &amp;ldquo;some testimonies&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;those statutes&amp;rdquo; - it&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;your testimonies&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;your statutes&amp;rdquo;.  Behind the law is the giver of the Law.  David&amp;rsquo;s longing, his desire, his love for God&amp;rsquo;s Word stems from his love for God himself.  I have no interest in reading a letter written by someone I don&amp;rsquo;t know - maybe a little if the author is famous, and I know &lt;em&gt;of&lt;/em&gt; them a bit.  But show me a letter written to me by my wife, and you bet I want to read it - I may even keep it filed away and pull it out periodically to re-read it.  I love that letter, because &lt;em&gt;she&lt;/em&gt; wrote it, and I love her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to be like David.  I want my love for God to be so deep, so intense, so intentional that his Word becomes something I desire, something I am consumed with longing for, something I love.  Maybe I&amp;rsquo;m not there yet.  I still struggle through some passages at times - I struggle to see the &lt;em&gt;person&lt;/em&gt; behind the words as clearly as David did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really want to be the kind of person who, when asked &amp;ldquo;Name one thing you never tire of&amp;rdquo;, would be able to say with David:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your testimonies are my heritage forever, for they are the joy of my heart. - Psalm 119:111&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lord, help me love your Word - but not just because of the words themselves.  Help me to love your Word because I love you.  Incline my heart to your testimonies, and not to selfish gain! Turn my eyes from looking at worthless things; and give me life in your ways. (Psalm 119:36-37)  Amen.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Being an Expert</title>
      <link>http://faith.rosborough.ca/being-an-expert/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Dec 2011 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://faith.rosborough.ca/being-an-expert/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I had a student recently ask, &amp;ldquo;Doesn&amp;rsquo;t it make you sad that there&amp;rsquo;s so many things in the world, and we can&amp;rsquo;t be an expert on all of them?&amp;rdquo;  Her frustration was stemming (I think) from her uncertainty about her future career path, and her interest in too many things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, I think it&amp;rsquo;s precisely that problem that makes life interesting.  It&amp;rsquo;s why, after thirty-some years, I&amp;rsquo;m still not really a &amp;ldquo;know-it-all&amp;rdquo;, even if I&amp;rsquo;d like to think so.  It&amp;rsquo;s why I can still sit down at my computer to learn something about home repair, something about computer science, something about biology, something about God.  In fact, the deeper you get into a particular field, it would seem that the more you realize there is to know.  I am constantly discovering that, in the fields in which I am the most conversant, I am very far from considering myself an &amp;ldquo;expert&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s a good thing!  We&amp;rsquo;re designed to want to learn, even if at times perhaps the school system seems designed to stifle that desire.  We will never run out of things to learn.  The implication, then, is that we need to make some choices about what&amp;rsquo;s worth learning.  There&amp;rsquo;s a lot of options out there, but where ought I spend my time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The author of the book of Romans suggests a great field of study:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, the depth of the riches and wisdom and knowledge of God! How unsearchable are his judgments and how inscrutable his ways! (Romans 11:33, ESV)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We never get to the point where we&amp;rsquo;ve exhausted the Bible, where we&amp;rsquo;ve fully explored the depths of the riches and wisdom and knowledge of God.  Perhaps our inability to know what there is to know about biology or computers is only a vague reflection of our inability to exhaust these depths which the writer of Romans is so enamoured with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, does it make me sad to find that I can&amp;rsquo;t be an expert in everything?  No, it encourages me with the realization that I&amp;rsquo;ll never run out of opportunities to discover, learn, and grow closer to God.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Value of the Kingdom of Heaven</title>
      <link>http://faith.rosborough.ca/the-value-of-the-kingdom-of-heaven/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2011 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://faith.rosborough.ca/the-value-of-the-kingdom-of-heaven/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What matters to you? If you asked me what matters most in life, I would &lt;em&gt;tell&lt;/em&gt; you that the most important thing in my life is God. But would you see that from the way I live? If, instead of asking, you just watched me carefully, observed what I spend my time doing, you&amp;rsquo;d probably think that my job, my kids, my wife, and food are what really matter to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matthew 13:44-46 says:
&amp;gt; “The kingdom of heaven is like treasure hidden in a field. When a man found it, he hid it again, and then in his joy went and sold all he had and bought that field.
&amp;gt; “Again, the kingdom of heaven is like a merchant looking for fine pearls. When he found one of great value, he went away and sold everything he had and bought it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two men in these parables not only &lt;em&gt;knew&lt;/em&gt; that they had found something of incredible value, they realized that it was worth so much more than everything else they had - and then they acted on it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Weight of Glory</title>
      <link>http://faith.rosborough.ca/the-weight-of-glory/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jul 2011 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://faith.rosborough.ca/the-weight-of-glory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was recently co-leading a Bible study for teen workers at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.morningstarbiblecamp.com&#34;&gt;Morning Star Bible Camp&lt;/a&gt;. It was a great opportunity to stop and think about what&amp;rsquo;s really important in the Christian life. We decided to focus on discipleship - which, of course, is a pretty broad topic. One of the discussions we had was around counting the cost of being a disciple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luke 14:25-35 (NIV) puts it pretty bluntly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;25 Large crowds were traveling with Jesus, and turning to them he said: 26 “If anyone comes to me and does not hate father and mother, wife and children, brothers and sisters—yes, even their own life—such a person cannot be my disciple. 27 And whoever does not carry their cross and follow me cannot be my disciple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;28 “Suppose one of you wants to build a tower. Won’t you first sit down and estimate the cost to see if you have enough money to complete it? 29 For if you lay the foundation and are not able to finish it, everyone who sees it will ridicule you, 30 saying, ‘This person began to build and wasn’t able to finish.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;31 “Or suppose a king is about to go to war against another king. Won’t he first sit down and consider whether he is able with ten thousand men to oppose the one coming against him with twenty thousand? 32 If he is not able, he will send a delegation while the other is still a long way off and will ask for terms of peace. 33 In the same way, those of you who do not give up everything you have cannot be my disciples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;34 “Salt is good, but if it loses its saltiness, how can it be made salty again? 35 It is fit neither for the soil nor for the manure pile; it is thrown out.
“Whoever has ears to hear, let them hear.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, we&amp;rsquo;re to carefully consider whether we wish to call ourselves a disciple of Jesus. Being a disciple does not come without cost - indeed, Jesus uses a powerful metaphor to describe what being a disciple is like: &amp;ldquo;whoever does not carry their cross and follow me cannot be my disciple&amp;rdquo;. Perhaps, far-removed as we are (at least in Canada) from capital punishment, and particularly by such abominable means, this metaphor has lost some of its impact. But there&amp;rsquo;s no doubt that the people standing around Jesus on that road would have understood with perfect clarity the weight of Jesus&amp;rsquo; words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My students will tell you that I&amp;rsquo;m one for the &amp;ldquo;negative&amp;rdquo; bits, and perhaps it&amp;rsquo;s harder for me to consider the positive than the negative. So, it&amp;rsquo;s easy for me to consider &amp;ldquo;counting the cost&amp;rdquo; of discipleship. But, as my co-leader in the Bible study pointed out, &amp;ldquo;counting the cost&amp;rdquo; leaves you with a completely unbalanced balance-sheet. When one sits down to build a tower (or, in her example, to renovate and &amp;ldquo;flip&amp;rdquo; a house), you don&amp;rsquo;t only count what it will cost, but you count what it will be worth in the end. Elsewhere, Jesus puts it like this (Matthew 13:44-46, NIV):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;44 “The kingdom of heaven is like treasure hidden in a field. When a man found it, he hid it again, and then in his joy went and sold all he had and bought that field.
45 “Again, the kingdom of heaven is like a merchant looking for fine pearls. 46 When he found one of great value, he went away and sold everything he had and bought it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These men realized that the kingdom of heaven was worth more than everything they had. That&amp;rsquo;s why they were happy to go out and sell everything - they recognized it to be the best investment they could make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It somehow doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem very &amp;ldquo;Christian&amp;rdquo; to think about rewards and benefits when thinking about discipleship. It seems much more pious to think about cost. And yet, there it is - the promise of staggering reward. C.S. Lewis, in a sermon entitled The Weight of Glory, deals with this sense that it&amp;rsquo;s somehow improper to consider the wonderful rewards that God has in store for us. This is a sermon that is well-worth reading in it&amp;rsquo;s entirety, but the introduction goes something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you asked twenty good men to-day what they thought the highest of the virtues, nineteen of them would reply, Unselfishness. But if you asked almost any of the great Christians of old he would have replied, Love. You see what has happened? A negative term has been substituted for a positive, and this is of more than philological importance. The negative ideal of Unselfishness carries with it the suggestion not primarily of securing good things for others, but of going without them ourselves, as if our abstinence and not their happiness was the important point. I do not think this is the Christian virtue of Love. The New Testament has lots to say about self-denial, but not about self-denial as an end in itself. We are told to deny ourselves and to take up our crosses in order that we may follow Christ; and nearly every description of what we shall ultimately find if we do so contains an appeal to desire. If there lurks in most modern minds the notion that to desire our own good and earnestly to hope for the enjoyment of it is a bad thing, I submit that this notion has crept in from Kant and the Stoics and is no part of the Christian faith. Indeed, if we consider the unblushing promises of reward and the staggering nature of the rewards promised in the Gospels, it would seem that Our Lord finds our desires, not too strong, but too weak. We are half-hearted creatures, fooling about with drink and sex and ambition when infinite joy is offered us, like an ignorant child who wants to go on making mud pies in a slum because he cannot imagine what is meant by the offer of a holiday at the sea. We are far too easily pleased.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>It Takes the Whole of Life</title>
      <link>http://faith.rosborough.ca/it-takes-the-whole-of-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jul 2008 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://faith.rosborough.ca/it-takes-the-whole-of-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I got reading a bit of Seneca’s &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikisource.org/wiki/On_the_shortness_of_life&#34;&gt;On the Shortness of Life&lt;/a&gt; this afternoon. Seneca was a Stoic philosopher, meaning that he belonged to a camp that “preached freedom from passion by following reason” (&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stoicism&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seneca’s main point is that it’s pointless to complain about how short life is. Life, he says, is plenty long enough; the main problem is that we waste most of it.  It’s a valid point, from my way of thinking at least. Seneca’s suggestion, of course, is that we’d do a lot better with things if we just spent all our time studying philosophy. As much as I like philosophy, I don’t think that’s the example Jesus would have us follow, however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What particularly struck me, though, was a comment buried way down in the middle of Chapter 7. Seneca says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It takes the whole of life to learn how to live, and – what will perhaps make you wonder more – it takes the whole of life to learn how to die.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frankly, the quote comes off a bit like meaningless pseudo-intellectualism to me. What do you mean it takes the whole of life to learn how to die? Surely lots of people actually &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; die without having figured it all out. But how about the first part? How do we learn how to live?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On one level, the Christian life is pretty simple. We are to love the Lord with all our heart, soul, mind, and strength. We’re to love our neighbour as ourselves. Everything else hangs on that. You can read it, you can understand the principle, in around a minute or so. On another level, though, it’s a life-long process. Tozer, in chapter one of &lt;em&gt;The Pursuit of God&lt;/em&gt;, cries out to God to help him to desire God more; it seems the more we do know God, the more realize we need him even more still.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am glad that, although some people may try to convince us otherwise, the good life isn’t achieved by a Stoic renouncing of all of the pleasures of life and dedication to pondering high thoughts. The good life, for the Christian, is lived in relationships: first with God, then with those around us.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crucified to the World</title>
      <link>http://faith.rosborough.ca/crucified-to-the-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jan 2008 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://faith.rosborough.ca/crucified-to-the-world/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We had a visitor at church today, a guy who had never been there before. When I was talking to him between services, he was telling us how much God had been doing for him and working in his life. Then he gave us a specific example - it turned out that last night he slept outside our local bank, under the awning, after getting ditched by some friends miles away from the shelter where he could have had a bed for the night. It got down to about -15°C last night (with the wind-chill), so it was a pretty serious situation. When he woke up this morning, he found himself covered in a blanket. If someone hadn&amp;rsquo;t put that blanket on him last night, he might just not have woke up, period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sat there about 3 feet away from this guy, this morning, using my 32gb iPod Touch to find the passage that the preacher was on. Now, I&amp;rsquo;ve been preaching at my students lately about my iPod Touch, and how it represents my own selfishness, my me-first consumerism, my &amp;ldquo;buy-in&amp;rdquo; to the world&amp;rsquo;s view of things. I&amp;rsquo;ve been comparing it to the BMW that Tony Campolo talked about way back when, when he said he didn&amp;rsquo;t figure Jesus would have a BMW in his driveway as long as there were poor people in Haiti (or, for that matter, in the seats in my church). For me, I drive a &amp;lsquo;93 Civic, so I felt pretty good about myself until I thought about that 32gb iPod Touch that I&amp;rsquo;d recently bought. When I bought it, I stood in the Costco for a good 15 minutes, trying to come up with a reasonable justification why I needed not just an iPod Touch, but the 32gb version. The thing cost me about $500.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The preacher this morning was preaching from the end of Galatians. He got to this passage this morning, which I finally dug up on my iPod Touch:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;May I never boast except in the cross of our Lord Jesus Christ, through which the world has been crucified to me, and I to the world. Neither circumcision nor uncircumcision means anything; what counts is a new creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Galatians 6:14-15&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sat there, feeling rather uncomfortable. What does it mean to be crucified to the world? What does it mean to be a new creation? Is there anything about me that &lt;em&gt;doesn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; shout &amp;ldquo;I love the world!&amp;rdquo;, but rather says &amp;ldquo;I love God&amp;rdquo;? Does my willingness to rush out and drop $500 on an electronic gadget that I really don&amp;rsquo;t need at all, while a guy sleeps outside the bank 2 blocks from my house, nearly freezing to death, say &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m a new creation&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think if the &amp;ldquo;world has been crucified to me&amp;rdquo;, my attitude about the things of the world, the &amp;ldquo;stuff&amp;rdquo;, the &amp;ldquo;lust of the flesh&amp;rdquo;, the &amp;ldquo;pride of life&amp;rdquo;, ought to be different than the attitudes of those who are &amp;ldquo;of the world&amp;rdquo;. Why is it that, so often, and perhaps most obviously around Christmas time, we let ourselves become enthralled with things?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>